<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
    <body>

        <release version="1.4.0" date="2008-11-31" desc="1.4 release">
            <!--Bug Fixes-->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix" issue="1819841">
                Update backport-concurrent version to 3.1. This version is available for all versions of Java including 6.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix" issue="1880042">
                Tuned a few unit tests use of Thread.sleep due to the Windows timing service of inaccurate aperture.
                Some tests that used an added 10ms to allow for Windows now allow for 20ms, based on research published
                in this bug report.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix" issue="1880042">
                Removed one last thread renaming method. The others were removed in 1831446. Thanks to Diogo Quintela for
                pointing this out.
            </action>
        </release>

        <release version="1.4.0-beta2" date="2008-01-01" desc="1.4.0 beta2 release">
            <!--Bug Fixes-->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix" issue="1819841">
                NPE in MulticastKeepaliveHeartbeatReceiver when accessing processingThreadPool during startup.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix" issue="1816084">
                RMIAsynchronousCacheReplicator flushReplicationQueue change to speed it up and remove pausing. Thanks to
                Kyle Sampson for this one.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix" issue="1811875">
                RegisteredEventListeners is not thread-safe where listeners are being added and removed during operation.
                Fixed. Thanks to Geoffrey Arnold for pointing this out. Also removed final from class.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix" issue="1828351">
                CacheStatistics causes a NPE if used for fresh caches. Fixed.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix" issue="1831446">
                Dropped thread renaming in SelfPopulating cache. A debug feature that has probably outlived its usefulness.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix" issue="1831817">
                cache.getAllWithLoader should use a loadAll method for any keys not present in the cache rather than loading
                individually. This is a performance optimisation. Fixed.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix" issue="1846461">
                Division by zero in RMIBootstrapCacheLoader.java where elements are non-null but empty, which causes
                bootstrap to fail, although gracefully. Fixed.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix" issue="1831755">
                Style issue. Abuse of Exceptions. Fixed.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix" issue="1831823">
                JCache.getAll wraps values in Element. Fixed.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix" issue="1802513">
                Replication Thread of Default Cache not disposed. Fixed.
            </action>
        </release>


        <release version="1.4.0-beta" date="2007-08-26" desc="1.4 beta release">

            <!--Features-->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Add CacheLoaders to ehcache configuration and core classes.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Add CacheExceptionHandlers. The enable an exception handler to be registered with a cache so that it is called
                on exception rather than the exception being thrown.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Add CacheExtensions. This is a generic facility which holds a reference to a cache and is bound to the cache lifecycle,
                making possible a wide variety of extensions to behaviour.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="update" issue="1737269">
                Add a version number to the ehcache jar manifest as is the Apache convention.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="update" issue="1752251">
                Include all required libraries in the Sourceforge tarball download.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="update" issue="1756338">
                Updated FAQ and Dependency chapters in the documentation and the Release Notes to point out that backport-concurrent
                for Java 5 is not compatible with Java 6, but the Java 4 version is.
            </action>

            <!--Bug Fixes-->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix" issue="1744643">
                LfuMemoryStore did not support Non-Serializable objects.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix" issue="1755263">
                Excessive CPU and (debug) logging when multicast send fails. Added a sleep to reduce the log spam
                when multicast is being blocked by a firewall. Continuous log messages obscure the network configuration
                issue. Thanks to Ronald Tschal for the bug report and patch.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix" issue="1759740">
                NPE during CacheManager shutdown with persistent disk cache only where the maxElementsOnDisk=1.
                Thanks to James Shaw for the bug report.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix" issue="1753349">
                i18n issue in the PageFragmentCachingFilter. Thanks to David Sheldon for the bug report and fix.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix" issue="1739612">
                ManualRMICacheManagerPeerProvider.listRemoteCachePeers lists no peers if one node is down. The manually configured
                cluster should list those peers that are available so that the cluster can continue until the missing node is restored.
            </action>

        </release>

        <release version="1.3.0" date="2007-06-11" desc="1.3 release">

            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix" issue="1728071">
                Where the Hibernate EhCacheProvider or SingletonEhCacheProvider is being used with a configurationResourceName to
                load an ehcache configuration other than default, when it is not found in the classpath, no warning or other failure
                occurs. Ehcache will instead load itself from defaults.
                Added a warning message to indicate that a configurationResourceName was specified but could not be found.
                This should simplify debugging. Thanks to Robert Watkins for raising this issue.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix" issue="1728780">
                RMIRegistry is now stopped if it was started by ehcache. This fixes a classloader memory leak on redeploy
                and reload in app servers. Thanks to Stefan Fleiter for supplying a patch.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix" issue="1728950">
                Tweak to bootstrap to check for expired elements. It will skip expired elements rather than failing the bootstrap.
                Thanks to Stefan Fleiter for supplying a patch.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix" issue="1732424">
                PropertyUtil.parseProperties using a JDK 1.5+ only feature. This issue was introduced in 1.3.0-beta3.
                Thanks to Ben Piper for pointing this out.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix" issue="1730999">
                DiskStore trace message for put back ups should only log when the DiskStore is backed up.
                Thanks to Stefan Fleiter for this one.
            </action>

        </release>

        <release version="1.3.0-beta3" date="2007-05-27" desc="Beta 3 for 1.3 release">

            <!-- Feature Changes  -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Add the ability to specify the property separator for the properties element in factory configurations.
                This is a new attribute propertySeparator that can be used in ehcache.xml configuration files.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="update">
                Enable the DiskStore to be programmtically pluggable in the Store hierarchy.
                Thanks to Matt Magoffin for the patch.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="update" fix="1725911">
                Applied minor patch to Element to allow it to be easily persisted using mechanisms other than Java Serialization.
                Thanks to Matt Magoffin for the patch.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix" issue="1715492">
                Problems when peer lookup fails when receiving heartbeats because heartbeat receiving is single-threaded. This issue
                affects dirty or misconfigured networks or clusters. It hardens ehcache so that valid peers can still form a cluster
                in the presence of Naming.lookup() problems with one or more peers. Thanks to Daniel Weill and Fredrik Bertilson for
                reporting this and Daniel for supplying a patch. The patch changes the heartbeat receiving implementation to be
                multi-threaded
                so that one bad peer cannot bring the others down.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="update" issue="1720152">
                Ehcache does asynchronous puts to the DiskStore. In previous version the amount of memory that could be used for spool
                buffering was
                unlimited. In very high load situations with limited memory this could cause OutOfMemory erros. This version introduces a
                diskSpoolBufferSizeMB
                configured per cache with a default of 30MB. Set this value to control the maximum amount of memory each cache DiskStore
                spool can consume.
                The default of 30MB should work well for backward compatibility. If you notice your DiskStore performance is affected
                negatively,
                increase diskSpoolBufferSizeMB.
            </action>
        </release>

        <release version="1.3.0-beta2" date="2007-5-1" desc="Beta 2 for 1.3 release">

            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix">
                Fix issue reported by Fredrik Bertilsson regarding peers entering and leaving a cluster, where the reentered peer would
                never get
                updates.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix" issue="1703340">
                Fixed RMICachePeer.getElements so that it does not allow null elements.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix" issue="1681308">
                DiskStore SpoolThread is too slow under Java 1.6. The Spooling Thread was set to 2, on a scale of 1 to 10
                from lowest to highest priority. Under JDK 1.6, this setting did not allocate enough CPU to enable the
                spool to be cleared in a given situation, whereas under JDK1.5 it did. This seems to be a bug in JDK6.
                The priority is now set to Thread.NORMAL_PRIORITY, which is 5.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="update" issue="1684223">
                Distributed cache - flushing replicationQueue on dispose. We should flush the replication queue rather than
                clear it on dispose.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix" issue="1704257">
                Fix clone problem introduced in 1.3-beta. This affects caches created from the default cache.
                Thanks to Erik Voorbraak for reporting this.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix" issue="1694609">
                Add note to sample ehcache.xml and documentation about the reserved cache name "default".
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="update">
                The shutdown hook is now turned off by default. Set the system property net.sf.ehcache.enableShutdownHook=true to turn it
                on.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix" issue="1706854">
                Document known issue with Tomcat. The presence of multiple &lt;Host&gt; entries in Tomcat's server.xml prevents
                replication from occuring. Thanks to David Patton for reporting this.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix" issue="1680964">
                Make clear in the JavaDoc documentation in Cache that RemoteCacheException can be thrown by calls to put,
                remove and removeAll when the cache replication policy is synchronous and a remote peer is unavailable.
                Thanks to Christopher G. Stach II for reporting this issue.
            </action>
        </release>

        <release version="1.3-beta1" date="2007-3-9" desc="Beta for 1.3 release">

            <!-- Feature Changes  -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Added a net.sf.ehcache.jcache package, which is an implementation of JSR107, backed by ehcache.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Added a net.sf.ehcache.management package, which contains full JMX instrumentation for ehcache.
            </action>

            <action dev="Tony Voss" issue="1588796" type="fix">
                Statistics Variables Need to be Longs. Changed internal representation to long in Cache, kept the
                direct getters for backwards compatible and changed the new Statistics class to be long based. Use
                getStatistics() to access the longs with out loss of precision.
                Reapplied. Somehow this got lost from 1.2.4.
            </action>
            <action dev="Chris Ryan" type="fix">
                Filter was rethrowing IOException as ServletException. The spec is clear that IOException is thrown
                as well. Catching these and rethrowing them as ServletException causes these IllegalStateException
                in Glassfish.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1616492" type="fix">
                JBoss, Spring and some other applications have shutdown hooks. A race condition existed in
                CacheManager#shutdown() such that multiple shutdown hook threads could attempt to shutdown
                the CacheManager at the same time. Added class synchronization to prevent this and also
                added a check for the system property net.sf.ehcache.disableShutdownHook=true which will disable
                addition of the shutdown hook. Reported by various people.

                Note: In ehcache-1.3-beta2 and higher the shutdown hook is off by default. The above property has
                no effect. Set the system property net.sf.ehcache.enableShutdownHook=true to enable it.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1618798" type="fix">
                Element#equals(Object) causes ClassCastException when the comparison object is not an Element. Fixed.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1636876" type="fix">
                GzipFilter corrupts UTF-8 encoded non-Latin characters. Fixed. Thanks to Matt Raible and Konstantin Kolinko
                for the bug report and Kolodin for the patch. This issue also affected the CachingFilter.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1664030" type="fix">
                Fix bug in RMIBootstrapCacheLoader.doLoad. If the first element in the remote cache is null, no bootstrapping
                will take place. Fixed. Thanks to Ben Piper for reporting this one and the fix.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix">
                Fix issue reported by Fredrik Bertilsson regarding peers entering and leaving a cluster, where the reentered peer would
                never get
                updates.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1661328" type="fix">
                Fix bug for the combination of Automatic Peer Discovery and synchronous
                bootstrapping.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="remove">
                Removed the JNDI manual listener and peer provider. This was proving difficult to maintain. Custom
                listeners and providers are pluggable and can be added as an extension to ehcache.
            </action>
        </release>

        <release version="1.2.4" date="2006-12-31" desc="Final 1.2.4 release">

            <!-- Feature Changes  -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="update">
                Consolidate shutdown hooks to one on each CacheManager instance.
            </action>
        </release>

        <release version="1.2.4RC" date="2006-11-26" desc="Minor release">

            <!-- Feature Changes  -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="remove">
                Dropped support for JDK1.3. Resulting changes are proper chained exceptions,
                and no longer requiring commons-collections. This enables some simplifications
                in the code base and eases maintenance.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck/Jody Brownell" type="add">
                Added a maxElementsOnDiskStore attribute to cache. This lets disk stores be
                bounded. ehcacheLFU eviction is used to decide which element to evict.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck/Jody Brownell" type="add">
                Combined the DiskStore's expiry and spool threads. They were competing for the
                same locks anyway. This reduces the maximum number of threads used from 2 to 1 per
                DiskStorwe.
            </action>
            <action dev="Tony Voss" issue="1588976" type="add">
                Enable the timeToLive to be set on the cacheManagerPeerProviderFactory. This enables
                the spread of multicast packets to be controlled from a single host to the Internet.
                The default is 1, which is the same as the Java default so the default behavior will not
                change for existing users.
            </action>

            <!-- Reported Bug fixes -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1574735" type="fix">
                Fix typo in lock timeout log message in BlockingCache. Thanks to Matt Magoffin
                for reporting this bug.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1579761" type="fix">
                Fix issue where it is not possible to specify a DiskStore path consistently
                on all operating systems. This is a workaround to a JDK bug. Always create
                paths like "java.io.tmpdir/cache". Any trailing characters to java.io.tmpdir
                added for windows and solaris will be removed and placed with a single file
                separator.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1563017" type="fix">
                Fixed NullPointerException on Cache.evictExpiredElements() and added some other NPE
                guards to Cache.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1585015" type="fix">
                Synchronous bootstrap and manual peer discovery combination does not work because
                the first cache to start always fails. This is normal and the CacheManager should
                cope with it. Added a catch and log a message when this happens. Thanks to Patrick
                Galley for the bug report.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1589004" type="fix">
                ehcache.xsd diskStore path defined as xs:NCName
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1589451" type="fix">
                Fix documentation error: Ehcache provider package inconsistent
            </action>

            <!-- Unreported Bug fixes -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1593099" type="fix">
                Fixed NPE when both DiskStore path is not configured and DiskStorePath is not being used.
                Thanks to mdillon for the patch. This was also reported under the above bug number.
            </action>

            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix">
                CachingFilter and its subclasses now work when upstream filters or servlets return
                404 or 302, 301.
            </action>

            <!-- Patches -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1584776" type="fix">
                Fixed rare ConcurrentModificationException in getBoundCachePeers. Thanks to Tony Voss
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1583996" type="fix">
                Harden heartbeat sender for IOExceptions and large peer sizes. Thanks to Tony Voss
                for the patch.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1584041" type="fix">
                Reduce network utilisation for distributed caching through the optimisation of only
                doing a Naming.lookup(url) when the url has not been seen before.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix">
                Various fixes to web package to make filters work on Sun Application Server 9 and Tomcat
                in addition to Orion. Add support for errors and redirects passing through filters.
            </action>
            <action dev="Tony Voss" issue="1592324" type="fix">
                Multiple multicast packets sends multiple heartbeats
            </action>
            <action dev="dguist" issue="1591711" type="fix">
                Infinite recursion in BlockingCache.getKeysNoDuplicateCheck
            </action>
            <action dev="Tony Voss" issue="1588796" type="fix">
                Statistics Variables Need to be Longs. Changed internal representation to long in Cache, kept the
                direct getters for backwards compatible and changed the new Statistics class to be long based. Use
                getStatistics() to access the longs with out loss of precision.
            </action>
        </release>

        <release version="1.2.3" date="2006-9-2" desc="Maintenance release">

            <!-- Feature Changes  -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1524597" type="add">
                Cache.remove doesn't fire listeners if element didn't exist. This stopped
                cluster
                removes from working where the local cache does not have the element cached.
                Thanks
                to Elijah Epifanov for reporting this one and arguing the case for this
                behaviour
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1540653" type="add">
                Allow references to ehcache.xsd in ehcache XML files. All of the ehcache.xml
                files
                have had the schema reference added. This allows easy validation of ehcache.xml
                configuration files using tools like Eclipse and IntelliJ. Thanks to Gabriel
                Klein
                for suggesting this.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1540657" type="add">
                Added a new property asynchronousReplicationIntervalMillis to the
                RMICacheReplicator factory
                configuration to control the interval at which it runs. The default is 1000ms,
                which
                is the value it was hardcoded too in earlier versions.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Added a new notifyRemoveAll cache event notification as requested by users.
                Called during Ehcache#removeAll() to
                indicate that the all elements have been removed from the cache in a bulk
                operation. The usual
                notifyElementRemoved is not called.
                This notification exists because clearing a cache is a special case. It is
                often
                not practical to serially process notifications where potentially millions of
                elements
                have been bulk deleted.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Added a new notifyElementEvicted cache event notification as requested by
                users.
                Called immediately after an element is evicted from the cache. Evicted in this
                sense
                means evicted from one store and not moved to another, so that it exists
                nowhere in the
                local cache. In a sense the Element has been
                <i>removed</i>
                from the cache, but it is different,
                thus the separate notification. The usual notifyElementRemoved is not called.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1523915" type="update">
                Asynchronous replication / soft references.
                There is a trade off between OutOfMemory risk and replication correctness.
                Change the RMIAsynchronousCacheReplicator so that Elements are SoftReference,
                not
                all EventMessages. The result is that put and update via copy may be
                SoftReference
                collected, but remove and update via remove will always go through.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="update">
                Change Cache#getQuiet so that cache statistics are not updated. This is a
                sensible
                API change and probably always should have worked this way.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="update">
                Open up some classes by removing final keyword and changing the constructors to
                public.
            </action>

            <!-- Reported Bug fixes -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1532610" type="fix">
                Fix isssue where a distributed cache can take up to a minute to shutdown. This
                issue
                affected web container and application server shutdowns.
                The fix is to unbind RMICachePeers before unexporting them. Thanks to Lennard
                Fuller
                and Peter Chiang for finding and fixing this hard one.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1529506" type="fix">
                Fixed a few broken links and inconsistencies in the documentation.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1542696" type="fix">
                Bad dependency scopes in Maven2 POM. Most dependencies are required only at
                test time.
                Changed the pom to reflect this.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1540322" type="fix">
                Synchronous replicators in a cluster can deadlock trying to replicate to each
                other.
                The deadlock gets resolved by a SocketTimeoutException depending on what you
                set it
                too. Reduce synchronization around gets, puts and removes so that listener
                notification
                is not synchronized, which resolves this problem.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1550043" type="fix">
                Fixed a bug where in BlockingCache and SelfPopulatingCache where
                setTimeoutMillis
                was set to a non zero value.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1548314" type="fix">
                Large TTL values cause expire time to be incorrect in Element. Changed
                ONE_SECOND from
                an int to a long which fixes the issue.
            </action>


        </release>

        <release version="1.2.2" date="2006-7-17" desc="Maintenance release to ehcache-1.2.1">

            <!-- Feature Changes  -->
            <action dev="Daniel Wiell" issue="1521843" type="add">
                Added a ShutdownListener which implements ServletContextListener for shutting
                down all CacheManagers in a web application.
            </action>

            <!-- Reported Bug fixes -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1516447" type="fix">
                If you put an Element with overridden TTL and TTI values and then replace it
                with an Element with defaults, the new Element lives forever. putQuiet is not
                affected by this bug. Thanks to Pete at Goodtech for finding this one.
                Note that a symptom of this bug for caches that overflow to disk is an
                endlessly
                growing .data file for the Cache.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix">
                Reduce the memory used by flushSpool() in DiskStore.
                See http://gregluck.com/blog/archives/2006/07/tuning_memory_u.html for details.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1521699" type="fix">
                Cache names with slashes cause problems. Tightened the validation code around
                setting a cache
                name. Now throw IllegalArgumentException if a cache name is null or contains
                '/'. Thanks to Daniel
                Wiell for repoting this one and suggesting the fix.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1517565" type="fix">
                Loading an element from the disk store fails in some circumstances due to
                classloading
                issues. This issue was created by a patch to fix 1324221 back in October 2005.
                Resolved
                by trying the new way and then, if a ClassNotFoundException is thrown, doing it
                the old way.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1513436" type="fix">
                CachingFilter should not change Thread name. Now sets it back to the original
                when done.
            </action>
        </release>

        <release version="1.2.1" date="2006-7-2" desc="ehcache-1.2.1">
            <!-- Feature Changes over 1.2.1RC -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1492900" type="add">
                Change Blocking cache to use a lock striping technique for its Mutexes. This
                limits the number
                of Mutexes to 100, rather than a number equalling the number of keys, while
                preserving excellent
                liveness and safety. Thanks to Olaf Krische for reporting this and Brian Goetz
                for assisting with
                a solution.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Change BlockingCache and SelfPopulatingCache to act as decorators for Ehcache.
                Remove now redundant
                BlockingCacheManager and SelfPopulatingCacheManager. Change signatures of these
                caches from Serializable
                to Object. This change is not backward compatible but no libraries use these,
                so developers can change
                over on their own projects.
            </action>

            <!-- Reported Bug fixes -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1190614" type="fix">
                This was reported by Victor Volle and is a duplicate of 1492900. Fixed.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1506399" type="fix">
                Changing all classloading to the context classloader is sometimes inconvenient.
                Fallback to
                ClassLoaderUtil.class.getClassLoader() if
                Thread.currentThread().getContextClassLoader()
                fails. Thanks to Robert Watkins for reporting this one.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1508623" type="fix">
                Debug messages generate excess String objects. Added logging level guards
                around about 6 debug log statements.
                Thanks to Derek Hulley for pointing this one out.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="fix">
                Harden all ehcache threads so that RuntimeExceptions and Errors do not stop
                them. This change, on its own, has been
                backported to a separate release, ehcache-1.2.0_01.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="update">
                Change spooling mechanism to use less memory, so as to avoid memory spikes.
            </action>
        </release>


        <release version="1.2.1RC" date="2006-6-4" desc="ehcache-1.2.1RC">
            <!-- Feature Changes over 1.2 -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Added the constructs package which was previously a separate module. The
                constructs package adds
                valuable functionality and given that the 1.2 jar size is large, can be added
                with only a small
                increase in jar size.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1483735" type="add">
                Allow zeroconf of RMICacheManagerPeerListenerFactory. A configuration
                &lt;cacheManagerPeerListenerFactory
                class="net.sf.ehcache.distribution.RMICacheManagerPeerListenerFactory"/&gt;
                will now work. The listener port will be automatically assigned a free port.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                New SingletonEhCacheProvider for use by Hibernate in situations where code has
                been written which relies
                on the singleton behaviour of ehcache-1.1 and earlier. Most code bases using
                Hibernate should not
                require this.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Allow cacheEventListenerFactory elements to be added to defaultCache in
                ehcache.xml. This allows
                caches created with CacheManager.addCache(String cacheName) to receive events.
                This can be used for
                example to set default replication settings in defaultCache.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                To complement full support foe default cache (above), added support for
                programmatic addition of caches
                which include CacheReplicators. Also support for removal of these caches with
                CacheManager.remove(String cacheName).
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Andy McNutt's JNDI-based manual RMI replication added. See ehcache.xml example
                for how to use.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Support tomcat 5.5 for the servlet filters. Tomcat integration testing, in
                addition to the Orion one, is also
                added to the full JUnit test process. Tomcat relies on Servlet 2.4 dispatcher
                INCLUDE and FORWARD directives
                for page fragment caching.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Support runtime setting of individual Element time to lives, time to idles and
                eternal overrides.
                If an override is set, the Element expiry ignores the Cache default.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Add a cache bootstrap mechanism. This is used to populate a cache when it is
                first initialized. An
                abstract factory, BootstrapCacheLoaderFactory has been defined along with an
                interface BootstrapCacheLoader.
                The initial concrete implementations are for RMI, so that a new cache entering
                a cluster gets bootstrapped
                from a randomly chosen peer.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Allow CacheManager instances to use the same ehcache.xml configuration.
                Automatically resolve conflicts
                for DiskStore and CacheManagerPeerListener. Log a warning that the conflict
                existed and what was done to
                resolve it along with a suggestion to either use ehcache in singleton mode or
                specify separate ehcache.xml
                configurations for each CacheManager instance.
            </action>

            <!-- Reported Bug fixes -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1480442" type="fix">
                Theoretically possible NPE if a MulticastRMICacheManagerPeerProvider is started
                and then stopped
                before a multicast socket connection can be established. Added guard for NPE.
                Thanks to Roman Kurmanowytsch
                for reporting the issue and a fix.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1485765" type="fix">
                Add shutdown hook to RMICacheManagerPeerListener so that, even if
                CacheManager.shutdown() is not called,
                processes still exit cleanly. This is a bug rather than a feature request
                because Cache has a shutdown
                hook to always cleanly shut down disk store, and ehcache should be consistent
                in supporting shutdown hooks.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1486858" type="fix">
                In GzipFilter and CachingFilter Gzipping an empty response body creates 20 byte
                responses. Fixed so that
                this situation is detected and a zero bytes gzipped body, with a content length
                also of 0 is returned. Can
                occur in 204 and 304 responses.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1488853" type="fix">
                Changed localhost lookup to a static in Cache, to avoid a potential bottleneck
                when creating and destroying
                large numbers of caches rapidly. Thanks to Derek Hully for the bug report and
                suggested fix.
            </action>
        </release>


        <release version="1.2" date="2006-4-25" desc="ehcache-1.2. ehcache-1.2 represents the addition of many new features while remaining
         backward compatible with 1.1.">
            <!-- Feature Changes over RC1-->
            <!-- Bug fixes -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1473833" type="fix">
                Changing the API to Object from Serializable breaks projects. Leave the
                existing Serializable
                API in place and add new constructors and methods for Object. Add
                getObjectValue and getObjectKey to
                Element.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1474363" type="fix">
                Closing Cache does not remove reference from DiskStore, preventing Garbage
                Collection of DiskStore and
                Cache
                on dispose of a cache. Fixed to set Cache reference to null on dispose. Thanks
                to Felix Meschberger for
                the patch.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1474360" type="fix">
                Closing Cache does not remove shutdown hook, preventing Garbage Collection of a
                Cache with a persistent
                DiskStore on dispose of a cache. Fixed to remove the shutdown thread after
                dispose.
                Thanks to Felix Meschberger for the patch.
            </action>
        </release>


        <release version="1.2rc1" date="2006-4-17" desc="ehcache-1.2 release candidate 1. ehcache-1.2 represents the addition of many new features while remaining
         backward compatible with 1.1.">
            <!-- Feature Changes -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="update">
                License updated to Apache 2.0.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="update">
                Following many requests, ehcache no longer requires that Elements contain
                Serializable keys and values.
                Ehcache will gracefully degrade for those operations which require
                Serialization. In particular the
                MemoryStore and event listeners can be used with Non Serializable elements.
                WARNING error messages are
                logged when an operation cannot be completed because the key or value is not
                Serializable.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="update">
                Feature Request 1458049 Wrap original exceptions during configuration.
                Added an intial cause Throwable field to CacheException to facilitate easier
                reporting without
                breaking pre JDK1.4 compatibility.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="remove">
                Removed the old Hibernate plugin from the code base. It has been deprecated
                since the beginning of the
                1.2 beta series. The plugin is being actively maintained in the
                Hibernate project. Any project still using net.sf.ehcache.hibernate.Plugin
                should change their
                Hibernate configurations to org.hibernate.cache.EHCacheProvider.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Feature Request 1081071. Added the ability to specify subdirectories under
                System Property paths. e.g.
                java.io.tmpdir/one
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Feature Request 1025706. Added the ability to specify a system property,
                net.sf.ehcache.disabled=true,
                to
                easily disable ehcache. A disabled cache works fully but discards and Elements
                added to it.
            </action>

            <!-- Bug fixes -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1432458" type="fix">
                Add protections to the DiskStore spoolThread against programming errors in
                Elements that can cause it to
                die.
                Secondly, if it does die, disable adding elements to the DiskStore and log an
                error, so as to gracefully
                degrade.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1369073" type="fix">
                flush() was using up to double the memory used by a MemoryStore during flush()
                which could cause an
                OutOfMemory error on shutdown if memory was constrained. flush no longer causes
                any memory spike.
                Thanks to Sergey Nekoval for reporting the bug.
            </action>
        </release>


        <release version="1.2beta5" date="2006-3-26" desc="Covers beta1 - beta 5 releases. ehcache-1.2 represents the addition of many new features while remaining
         backward compatible with 1.1.">
            <!-- Feature Changes -->
            <action dev="Surya Suravarapu" type="add">
                Introduced new caching policies in addition to the standard LRU. FIFO and LFU
                were added. LRU remains
                the default unless explicitly set in each cache's configuration. Thanks to
                Surya Suravarapu for working
                with me on these. The documentation has a new section on caching policies and
                when to use what.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Introduced CacheManagerEventListener and CacheEventListener interfaces and
                default implementations.
                These can be configured in ehcache.xml or set programmatically. Thanks to steve
                at jofti dot com for
                help with the specification for these.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                After requests from Jo Walnes, Paul Hammant and others, I have added normal
                instance constructers to
                CacheManager which do not act as singletons. The factory singleton methods
                remain for backward
                compatibility. CacheManager can now be constructed with a Configuration object
                programmatically.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Since version 1.1, ehcache has had a persistent diskStore, which makes it
                suitable for storing
                application state. Added a flush method so that, if the cache is
                diskPersistent, it can be
                programmatically flushed, in addition to the automatic flush which happens at
                shutdown.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Pluggable Distributed Caching. The default implementation supports cache
                discovery via multicast or
                manual configuration. Updates are delivered asynchronously or synchronously via
                custom RMI connections.
                Additional discovery or delivery schemes can be plugged in by third parties.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                DiskStore is now up to 12 times faster in certain operations and much more
                scalable.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Significant (up to 7 fold) DiskStore performance increases, after introduction
                of finer grained
                threading. Thanks to Robert Watkins for reporting on the performance limits.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="update">
                Clover test coverage raised to 86%.
            </action>


            <!-- Feature Requests -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="update">
                Feature Request 431481 Distributed: The ability to notify cache event listeners
                excluding
                CacheReplicators
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="update">
                Feature Request 1431393 Events from remote in distributed cache should be
                received by any non
                CacheReplicator listeners
            </action>

            <!-- Patches -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="update">
                Patch 1158788. Fix for dependencies list... MemoryStore.java to remove Apache
                commons-collections for
                JDK1.4
                users
            </action>

            <!-- Bug fixes -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1122734" type="fix">
                change default configuration to use context classloader
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1324221" type="fix">
                Fix for DiskStore to deserialize using
                Thread.currentThread().getContextClassLoader()
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1261613" type="fix">
                CacheManager.shutdown now uses a Class rather than an instance lock.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1237017" type="fix">
                Configurator gets a file not found when files contain spaces.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1332728" type="fix">
                DiskStore degrades under load.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1079529" type="fix">
                Change classloader to Thread.currentThread().getContextClassLoader() for
                ehache.xml.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1414674" type="fix">
                DiskStore data file is not deleted when index is corrupt.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1224325" type="fix">
                JavaDoc documentation fix for element.getLastAccessTime returns 0 for element
                just created
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1247019" type="fix">
                Documentation should advise using the Hibernate supplied plugin rather than the
                older one in
                ehcache which is now deprecated.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="" type="fix">
                Fix bug introduced in 1.2 beta series. Removed Boolean.parseBoolean and
                java.util.Queue which were
                introduced
                in the JDK1.5 API to preserve backward compatibility.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="" type="fix">
                Fix bug introduced in 1.2 beta series. Changed ant script to avoid compiling
                with clover in dists
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1410374" type="fix">
                Fix bug introduced in 1.2 beta series. Cannot load configuration from jar (or
                any non-file URL).
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1432074" type="fix">
                Fix bug introduced in 1.2 beta series. NPE on
                RMICacheManagerPeerProviderFactory when rmiUrls not
                specified. Now throws a meaningful CacheException.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1445694" type="fix">
                Fix bug introduced in 1.2 beta series. Deadlock on deserialization of a cache
                entry. Thanks to Felix
                Meschberger
                for reporting the bug and uploading a patch.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1457268" type="fix">
                Fix bug introduced in 1.2 beta series. Caches created with
                Cache.addCache(String) share a
                RegisteredEventListeners instance.
                Thanks to Olaf Ontaine for for reporting the bug and showing how it happens.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1451780" type="fix">
                Fix bug introduced in 1.2 beta series. RMIAsynchronousCacheReplicator
                mishandling non-copy updates.
                Thanks to Randy Puro for a patch.
            </action>
        </release>


        <release version="1.1" date="2004-11-23" desc="Maintenance release">

            <!-- Feature Changes -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="remove">
                Split out the entire constructs package. These are now in a new subproject:
                ehcache-constructs, which
                has been released.
                See http://ehcache.sf.net/ehcache-constructs for more details.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="remove">
                removed the dependency on Doug Lea's concurrency library.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Add new documentation on cache configuration and hibernate performance tuning.
            </action>

            <!-- Bug Fixes -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="1063908" type="fix">
                Extra check to make sure that we always close persistent disk store's
                FileInputStream in the
                rare case where the ObjectInputStream is null.
            </action>

        </release>

        <release version="1.0" date="2004-9-28" desc="Stable release">

            <!-- Feature Changes -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Added SelfPopulatingCacheManager
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Added a new diskExpiryThreadIntervalSeconds configuration option to
                ehcache.xml, to allow
                tuning of the expiry thread per cache.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Added a new diskPersistent feature and configuration option. diskPersistent
                makes disk stores
                persistent between CacheManager and JVM restarts. It enables very long held
                caches to be configured,
                useful
                for very expensive cache entries that are long lives, such as mapping geocodes.
            </action>

            <!-- Bug Fixes -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="" type="fix">
                Expiry Thread now has a default time of 2 minutes, not 25.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="" type="fix">
                Expiry Thread now dies immediately on DiskStore disposal.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="" type="fix">
                cache.calculateInMemorySize() now returns a non-zero value
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="" type="fix">
                Bug 1025130 - Null Pointer Exception when no default cache configured. Now we
                throw a CacheException
                with a
                meaningful message.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="" type="fix">
                Bug 1025128 IBM Websphere alway requires commons-collection.jar, even though it
                is never used. Updated
                requirements
                to note this.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="" type="fix">
                Patch 1030960. JDK1.4 and higher now chain exception thrown from
                SelfPopulatingCache.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="" type="fix">
                1033061 Fix to Thread naming in SelfPopulatingCache so that the old name is
                always put back.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="" type="fix">
                1003659 build script unfriendly to IDE: IDE builds should now work.
            </action>

        </release>


        <release version="0.9" date="2004-7-5" desc="Additional release">

            <!-- Feature Changes -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                ehcache.xml cache definitions can now omit timeToIdle and/or timeToLive, which
                are now optional
                attributes.
                This will make cache config easier to read for eternal caches.
                Either omitting the attributes or setting them to 0 causes them not to be
                considered when calculating
                expiry.
                Earlier versions of ehcache would have immediately expired all elements if
                either attribute was set to
                0,
                so this change should not break any existing code.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Added getQuiet and putQuiet methods to Cache. These methods are the same as get
                and put
                but do not affect statistics.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Implemented an Element clone method.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Added calculateInMemorySize() method to Cache to measure the approximate size
                of a cache's
                memory footprint.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="update">
                Increased Clover test coverage to above 80%.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="update">
                Added many new tests for idle expiry.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="update">
                Added tests for the new constructs package. These tests demonstrate concurrency
                performance
                differences between blocking cache designs based on notify/notifyAll and Doug
                Lea's concurrency package.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="update">
                Test new xml format scenarios for eternal, time to idle and time to live
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="update">
                Started adding performance tests to ensure there are no regressions over time.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Added a new constructs package. There are blocking, self populating and self
                populating collections
                caches.
                These are all pull-through caches. They are useful where the cost of creating
                an entry is high.

                Details follow:
                <![CDATA[
                BlockingCache - a cache which blocks subsequent threads until the first read thread
                populates a cache entry
                <br/><br/>
                SelfPopulatingCache - a read-through cache. A cache that populates elements as they are requested
                without requiring the caller to know how the entries are populated. It also enables refreshes
                of cache entries without blocking reads on the same entries.
                <br/>     <br/>
                SelfPopulatingCollectionsCache - a SelfPopulatingCache that adds threading safety where it is known
                in advance that all entries will be collections.
                <br/>          <br/>
                The package is useful for, inter alia, :
                <br/><br/>
                - Web Page caches          <br/>
                - Search Engine caches<br/>
                <br/><br/>
                See the tests for examples of how to use this package.
                <br/><br/>
                This package requires Doug Lea's concurrency library. A copy is provided in the tools directory
                when you check out the project by SVN. Or, you can get it from http://gee.cs.oswego.edu/dl/cpj/
                Note that if you are not using the constructs package, you do not need the concurrency library.
                ]]>
            </action>

            <!-- Bug Fixes -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="" type="fix">
                JavaDoc fixups
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="" type="fix">
                Fixed time to idle which was not expiring elements after the idle time had
                expired. This feature did
                not seem to be getting used. It is now useable. Fixed the test which was also
                broken
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="" type="fix">
                Fixed bugs with getSize and getKeys, which were not checking for duplicate keys
                between
                the memory and disk stores.
            </action>
        </release>


        <release version="0.8" date="2004-5-15" desc="Additional features">

            <!-- Feature Changes -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Investigated a Hibernate SessionFactory bug and clarified it was not a
                Hibernate bug. Added test.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Investigated a cache size possible bug and clarified it is not in EHCache.
                Added test.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Added Clover test coverage reporting. Clover instrumentation is not included in
                release jars.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Updated Hibernate testing to version 2.1.1
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Modified the Apache license at the request of the Apache Cocoon project.
            </action>

            <!-- Bug fixes -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="" type="fix">
                Fixed a very rare null pointer exception, when retrieving a cache entry.
            </action>

        </release>


        <release version="0.7" date="2004-1-2" desc="Bug fix release">

            <!-- Bug fixes -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="" type="fix">
                Cache Configuration
                Fixed null pointer exception where the disk store path was not specified when
                use disk store is set to
                false
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="" type="fix">
                JDK1.3 Compatibility Replaced JDK1.4 Exception constructors with simple message
                constructors compatible
                with JDK1.2 and 1.3
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="" type="fix">
                Problem with Element expiry
                Fixed bug where expiry checking on get was calling remove with the element
                rather than the key.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="" type="fix">
                Expire thread should not run if the cache is not active
                Changed the expire thread to while(active)
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="" type="fix">
                Expiry thread unnecessarily being created for eternal caches
                Skipped creating the expiry thread if caches are eternal.
            </action>
        </release>


        <release version="0.6" date="2003-12-8" desc="Bug fix release">

            <!-- Feature Changes -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="remove">
                Remove SoftReferences
                SoftReferences for cache element values has been replaced with standard
                references.
                The JDK 1.4.2 JVM was found to remove SoftReferences in normal operation,
                rather than
                the expected behaviour of use only to avoid memory exhaustion. Caches will now
                behave deterministically. Element values will only be removed when the element
                is
                garbage collected.
            </action>


            <!-- Bug fixes -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="" type="fix">
                Hibernate Cache Provider.
                Fixed bug where incompatible timestamps were generated
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="" type="fix">
                Time to Idle" documentation bug.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="" type="fix">
                Fixed documentation bug in ehcache.xml and ehcache-failsafe.xml where "Time to
                Live" was
                incorrectly referred to as "Time to Idle"
            </action>

        </release>


        <release version="0.5" date="2003-11-18" desc="Hibernate compatibility release">

            <!-- Feature Changes -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Changed from JDK1.4 Logging to Commons Logging. This is to permit JDK1.2 and
                JDK1.3 to use EHCache.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Added Apache Commons Collections LRUMap as an alternative backing Map for the
                MemoryStore. The
                java.util.LinkedHashMap has been retained and is used automatically for JDK1.4
                and higher.
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Added LICENSE.txt to the jar in the distribution
            </action>


            <!-- Bug fixes -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="" type="fix">
                Don't create a Disk Store when overflowToDisk="false" is set in ehcache.xml
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="" type="fix">
                toString() methods now report on all fields
            </action>
            <action dev="Greg Luck" issue="" type="fix">
                Fixed documentation bug in ehcache.xml and ehcache-failsafe.xml where "Time to
                Live" was
                incorrectly referred to as "Time to Idle"
            </action>

        </release>


        <release version="0.4" date="2003-11-13" desc="First public release">

            <!-- Feature Changes -->
            <action dev="Greg Luck" type="add">
                Initial version, originally based on a fork from JCS plus donated patches.
            </action>

        </release>


    </body>
</document>
